So, we're very excited about the power
of AI agents. Uh more particularly in
particular is we started in June 2026.
And our interest was driven by this some
recent papers from DeepMind
uh FunSearch which demonstrated
early on that you can use AI to
uh improve the state-of-the-art
performance of
uh algorithms and then was followed by
uh Alpha Evolve uh showing that coding
agents uh can be used to improve the
SOTA of for some
uh you know, existing systems and
techniques.
And then Open Evolve was an open-source
version of uh Alpha Evolve which was
released around the same time. And
obviously, we have all these kind of
agents coding agents like Claude, Codex,
and Cursor.
Uh so,
you know,
triggered by this kind of events, um we
started to run a special seminar over
the summer last summer at Berkeley and
where the students uh system students
were using this uh AI
uh evolutionary uh agents
to apply as they applied to their own
system to their own research.
And in particular, we went all through
12 uh different projects.
And uh the results were quite impressive
or better than expected. So, these two
12 projects included um around seven uh
published work uh by the students in top
conferences in systems or AI um included
also some work in progress and um
some publications some some research
just published on archive.
And in 10 out of these 12 cases, we got
results which are better than SOTA. And
not only that, but it was very cheap to
use,
you know, the best models and Gemini and
OpenAI ChatGPT to get the results. So,
it was quite cheap and quite fast.
So, this a lot of excitement
and also since then,
we done a lot of work in the space.
In particular, we taught two graduate
classes, courses
the previous two semesters.
We wrote position papers. We launched
the ADRS blog series where ADRS stands
for AI-driven research for systems.
And of course, we like we are from
academia, so we published and we built a
bunch of systems and published a bunch
of papers.
So, everything started with very with
great expectations and the expectation
was that AI will disrupt the system
research the way we know it.
So, what happened actually with over the
past year? What was our experience?
So, what was the reality?
Well,
it is true that AI did improve our
research productivity.
It's great. It's been great for research
some providing some ideas, of course,
for
speeding up some paper writing.
So, no question has a very positive
impact on our productivity.
It did also become a big part of our
research agenda.
Like I just mentioned earlier on.
However, did it really disrupt the way
we do do the research? Did it allow us
to build new production systems in a
fraction of time we used to do.
Um did it allow us to come with new
research through truly new research
ideas? Well, the answer to those No, not
yet.
So, this talk is about trying to
understand why.
Uh what are what are the limitation we
encountered?
And I would say this is not only our
story, but the story of many other
people we talked
with uh
for the past uh several months.
Now, if you take a step back, the key
goal of an AI coding agent is to develop
a software system that meets a certain
level of assurance with acceptable
levels of risk as fast as possible and
as cheaply as possible.
Uh here the software assurance is an
ongoing process to establish
uh and maintain some justified
confidence
which is supported by credible credible
evidence from running the software that
the software system
um will satisfy some specific claims,
will have some specific properties and
in its deployment environment.
So, fundamentally you need to do that by
using the resources at your disposal.
And the resources come in three forms.
It's humans, agents, AI agents, and of
course compute. So, the question is how
to achieve our goal by best using these
resources. And if you think about this
as a framework
um or as a system, then the key question
to answer
is about what are the bottlenecks.
And then once you identify the
bottlenecks, you alleviate them or you
remove them if you can, and then you are
going to speed up the development.
So, let me give some of the motivating
examples. So, this is
a work we done recently, and the goal
here is to synthesize a key-value
storage system from scratch.
Um and you know, as everyone knows, it's
a pretty simple system, pretty simple
interface actually, where you associate
a key with a value, and you put that
pair key-value in the storage, and then
you can given the key, you can retrieve
the value.
And in this particular case, it was a
pretty simple setting. We We have only
one server, so no distributed
environment. Uh although the server was
a server was multi-threaded, so you have
concurrency.
The So, basically, you store the data on
the disk, and you cache in memory to um
retrieve it faster. And the goal was to
maximize the throughput, and
to evaluate it, we use this YCSB, which
is a well-known benchmark for such
workloads.
So, now in the process of using this
evolutionary AI agents to uh synthesize
a solution, we got one solution at some
point, which was six times faster than
all the previous solutions, a huge
improvement. So, why was that? Right? Of
course, you are curious to understand
what led to such a big improvement.
Well, it turns out that these benchmarks
generated values in a predictable way.
So, when you generate the value in the
benchmark, you know, you need to to say
what the value it is. And in this
particular case, it generated the value
by hashing from the key associated with
that value and a seed.
Now, the agent found this out. So, and
instead of storing the values, it
basically computed the values using this
predictive
function on the fly.
Which means that because you don't need
to store up the values, you only store
need to store up only the keys, you can
store a lot of more items in memory, so
the retrieve is going to be much faster,
hence the improvement we see.
Now, everyone knows this is kind of, you
know, reward hacking.
So, if you look about this reward
hacking,
you see it generate is actually is due
to two gaps, and this is the main topics
of my talks. One go gap, we call it
requirement gap.
So, you see in this case, the agent in
the specification were required to
return a value which was put associated
with a particular key. However, the user
intends the stakeholders, we are going
to call intent, was to store that value.
Right? Not only to return the value. So,
here is a gap. And then there is a model
gap in this particular based on the
workload
in the development versus deployment
environment. In the benchmarking, the
development environment contains
predictable values. However, in the real
world the deployment,
you have arbitrary values. So, here is
another gap.
So, now how is the solution typically
working
um in this case? So, let just take a
step back here. So, you have a bunch of
requirements, which basically describe
the system needs to be built,
performance goals, and so forth. And you
have a model,
which tries to abstract away the
deployment environment, and this is is
about where in the environment you are
going to be target the deployment, the
workload which you think is
representative of the real workload,
kind of the failures and things like
that. And now, the developer or an AI
agents take these requirements and the a
and generates a program, and then this
program is evaluated, right? And
evaluated you can have unit test,
end-to-end test, integration test, or
you can have contracts or formal
methods.
Now, if it passes this evaluation, or if
it is a evaluation, sorry, doesn't pass,
then you provide the feedback to the
developer and to the AI agents, and then
you are going to continue in a loop
until the program passes the evaluation,
and then you are going to deploy it.
The problem is again that the
requirements and the models are an
abstractions.
On one hand of the user intent, what the
user wanted the system to do, and the
real world where the system is going to
be deployed. And these are the delta
between those are the requirement gaps
you are talking about.
So, more being a little bit more
specific, the requirement gap is there
because the intent of the users is
broader than the requirement. And here
are some examples. There are omissions,
things that the system should do, but is
not specified, like store arbitrary
client values. There are exclusions,
like system things system should not do
and are not specified, like never expose
customer data. Trade-offs, like for
instance, a search has a 200-millisecond
SLA. If this SLA is exceed if this
deadline is exceeded, should you wait?
Should Should it Should Should you
return partial results or you should it
run a failure? And there are conflicts
which are not specified how to be
solved, like for instance, you want
personalization, but this needs chat
history, but privacy rules prohibit
retaining the chat history. How you are
going to resolve this trade-off it has
to be specified. Now, the model gap is
is the same
you have for the same reason because the
real real world is broader than the
model. So, the model gap is there. So,
other examples are the workload
predictable,
for instance, the workloads
have predictable benchmarks during the
development versus arbitrary development
arbitrary values during the deployment.
You have failures like fail stop test in
during the testing and Byzantine false
during the deployment. You have
dependencies like set table marks versus
changing the APIs in the physical
in in the deployment case. And you or
you can have adversary and drift and new
attacks or workloads
which happens after release.
So, these two gaps are responsible for
the reward hacking and the reward
hacking is arguably responsible for many
of the things you have seen recently in
the news like this agents escaping their
environments and going route.
Um it's also they are you can trace back
them to alignments and or misalignments
and hallucinations.
And a key challenge here is about under
representation.
Um so
and um
you know, because you can only judge
from available evidence and the evidence
is often incomplete. New evidence might
invalidate acceptance of a program P
during deployment. Examples are
implementation P developed
I I is an implementation developed in um
and you know, under the model
M which assume fail stop failures, then
you deploy this in practice and as long
as you have only fail stop failures in
the deployment environment, you are
good. The stakeholder accept the
implementation, but once you get a
failure like a Byzantine failure like a
corrupted memory, that's no longer
acceptable.
Now, why is closing these requirements
so you know,
gaps are hard.
So, first of all, intent might be
tacit,
contested, or changing. Fundamentally,
you don't know what you don't know,
right? You cannot think about all the
corner or future cases until you see
them, right? And this has been noticed
for the past decades in many
domains, software engineering, AI,
economics, with contracts, politics, and
so forth.
Um and you can also think about this
like from a pure solution perspective.
If you think about how you can close
them. Well, one way is to ask people
whenever there is many material change
on the deployment, you can ask people is
this good or not, or you can
create an oracle, a model, or a
simulator that predicts every material
judgment of the status of the
stakeholder.
Um the same story is a model. The model,
if you really think about you want a
good model, you need to prove that every
omitted aspect
wins from that real world in the model,
what what the model is missing, is
irrelevant for
um accept accept the validity of that
implementation. And you keep the claim
and the other one, this has to the
claims have to be valid
as the
as the world changes.
Okay? And again, has been a lot of work
here over the past decade pointing out
with this point and this kind of
fundamental gap between the model
using development and the real world.
Okay? So, again, here to illustrate why
it's hard, you can ask people, for
instance, to every time only the
changing environment to say, "Okay, is
this change materially important for the
model you are going to have?" Or you can
predict, you can simulate the real
world, right? But obviously, all these
direct giving the user direct access and
to or complete having complete
simulations are not feasible. Actually,
even if you have the direct access is
it's on one hand the cost and latency
can be prohibitive, but on the other
hand is like you cannot only can reason
for the existing evidence. You cannot
reason for things you have never seen
it. You haven't thought about. And
obviously for the model for the for the
deployment for the real world, you can
have a complete simulation. You can
think to have a simulation, but if you
want to have the simulation, that's
another model. So, you are back in
square one because you need to
demonstrate that the simulation there is
no gap between that simulation and
and the real world.
Now, the other thing I want to make and
is that Now, why we are talking about
this? Because we are we we have been
you know, like I like I said, these gaps
are there and have been there for
decades. People identify them, recognize
them. Well, one reason we are
emphasizing this because agents amplify
the gaps. And this are for several
reasons. It's context asymmetry. A
developer typically has more local and
system and organizational context about
a task than the agent the agent which
brings broader context but has less
specific
context about that task.
The other one which is very important,
AI there is much faster under fixed
requirements model and a fixed
evaluator, which means they discover and
exploit exploitation
much faster. Actually,
you know, the developers typically give
up or they are not
you know, to find any of these
exploitation even if they want, but the
model it because AI agent is much
faster, they are going to find it what
humans will never find.
And is deployment scale especially if
you are going now to have an automatic
deployment of this of this
uh
programs in production.
Um let me skip. Now, I want to say about
there is a third gap and
um I'll um and which I want to mention
is is and this is between the evaluator
and the requirement on one side and
requirement and model on the other side.
So, the question this gaps, uh you know,
it's uh illustrate it by
illustrate this gap is that you have an
evaluator. So, but passing this
evaluator
does it guarantee that the
implementation is going to
um
satisfy all
requirements under model, right, in all
possible executions? And in general, the
answer is no because, for instance,
you're you use kind of unit test and so
forth, so it's only a subset of test.
You can points you can show that for
these points, for these data points, for
these values, you satisfy the
requirements under RAM. But,
actually, there are ways you can do it
and you close the gap and this is formal
methods.
Um
and that's why we are not focusing as
much on this gap right now. However, the
reason I'm mentioning this gap is
because the using the formal specs
actually can widen requirements and
model gaps because of formal specs are
going
to be less expressive than kind of
natural language written requirements
and the models.
Um
So, finally, you know, like like I will
say, you know, does narrowing these gaps
help?
Uh yes, most actually most successful
report is so far are in domains with
narrower gaps. And there are um a
significantly work ongoing work to
narrow gaps in other domains. And here
are some examples. Formal mathematics.
In formal mathematics, model gap is
closed because
uh there you have formal semantics, you
have axiomatic systems which fully
defined your the world in which
the properties have to be spec- you
know, are going to to needs to be true.
The theorem has to be true. The
requirement gap still remains because
informal to formal translation still
remains. Capturing what is your intent
in a in a uh you know,
in a theorem and so forth. Uh hardware
systems. You know, for hardware system,
you have instructions at architecture,
you have RTL which bound the relevant
behavior. Of course, this doesn't close
a gap to physical effects which are
remaining outside the model.
Uh strong verification also might close
the evaluation gap. System optimization.
We are talking about system optimization
versus system synthesis. With system op-
optimization, you you are going to be
anchored of you know, code. And in this
code, it's going to capture the
interfaces, HKI, this functionality. So,
it's kind of narrowing model and
requirement gaps as compared with the
system synthesis, it really lacks this
anchor and must infer more from
incomplete requirements and models.
And finally, world models. Right? What
world models try to achieve is to narrow
the model gap by learning
the model's part of the model by
interacting with the deployment work.
Okay. So,
2 more minutes and I'll be done. Um
so, you know, so how can you close this
gap in general? Well, to close this gap
in general, you need another loop which
actually includes the intent, the user
intent, and the real world. And this is
the first step here is to have obs- to
observe and try to to de- to detect um
what are kind of the issues, unexpected
issues, misbehaviors. Then you need to
diagnose them, then you need to revise,
and you are going to revise the
requirements of fully improve some
requirements, improve the models,
improve the evaluators, which will
reduce the gaps. And you do this until
you are going to achieve you are assured
your level of assurance and risks.
And let me give back because I'm so you
know,
um
skip a few slides. Um so we've done
quite a bit of work in this area, and
but of course much more remains to be
done. And here are some pieces of work
we've done for instance for
the loop for development loop
evolutionary loop for AI agents uh for
reducing uh the evaluation gap um
for diagnosing
you know, tracing uh the intent of and
from the traces which represents a user
interaction with the systems or the
agent uh interaction with the real
world.
And uh obviously uh directly trying to
um um to reduce the um
to narrow the requirements and the model
gaps. So what are the takeaways? So here
the takeaways
from this presentation.
First, the model and requirement gaps
are fundamental and cannot be certified
as closed in an open and changing
environment. Again, because you don't
know what you don't know.
So therefore you can only narrow them.
The second one is like the humans will
remain in the assurance loop because
they are needed at least to narrow the
requirement gap because they own the
intent. And likely because they are
going to be in the in the assurance
loop, they are going to be the
bottleneck.
And the evaluation gap can be closed
using formal method, but the cost can be
increasing the modern requirement gaps
because a lack or the limited
expressivity
of the specification which are needed by
the formal method.
Finally, these are not new problems,
like I mentioned.
However, AI agent exacerbate them
because of the context asymmetry, speed,
and scale. They are going to find
and exploit this kind of gaps
much better, much faster than humans.
So, therefore, what what do we need to
do? We need to use the best practices in
software engineering and security and to
do to need to be more cautious and
meticulous than ever before. And of
course, do a lot of more and interesting
research to close these gaps. Thank you.
>> Thank you so much for starting us off.
What a wonderful talk. Uh next we have
Nick Harris. He's founder, CEO of
Lightmatter, and he'll be talking on
photonics is the future of computing.
>> All right, looks like we're getting
slides up. Uh great to be here at the uh
Agentyc AI Summit here at Berkeley. My
first visit to Berkeley. I'm I went to
MIT. Lots of love for Berkeley, but uh
yeah, good to be here. So, today I'm
going to be telling you about
Lightmatter and and some of the stuff
that we're doing.
Uh 10 minutes, so let's jump in.
If you zoom out on what's happening in
AI, and especially with the advent of
Agentyc AI workloads, which I remember
hearing about starting in, you know,
'25, which felt pretty early. Um really
what's going on is the world is under
undergoing a massive AI build out. We're
building data centers in Texas and
British Columbia that are using as much
power as the biggest cities on Earth. Uh
think about New York City, something
like 7 gigawatts. That's going to be a
pretty average data center in Texas in
Abilene.
Uh
you know, and why is this happening?
Like what's the motivation behind
building these uh energy consuming
objects that have, you know, 100 times
the density of a city? Why are we doing
this?
We can go to the next slide here.
My clicker is not clicking.
There we go.
So, here's why. Uh if you look over the
past several years at the run time for
AI models, how long can they uh run
given a complex task and have a 50%
chance of completing that task? That's
been growing obviously exponentially.
So, now we're at a spot where the latest
AI models can run for something like 24
hours and have a 50% chance of of
getting a problem solved. I don't know
anybody who can work for 24 hours
non-stop and have a 50% chance at
solving a hard technical problem.
Certainly I can't do it. And so, we're
on this trajectory uh I can't see any
saturation in the data, to be clear.
We're on this trajectory where AI models
are going to be solving harder and
harder, longer time horizon problems all
in one go. Uh so, it's a pretty
incredible capability that we're
unlocking. And this is what's underlying
the build out, the amount of energy that
we're going to spend, all the buildings,
the GPUs, the custom AI ASICs that are
going to be going into these buildings.
This is what underlies it. We're
starting to be able to have machines
perform calculations and solve problems
that are incredibly hard for humans, and
we're compressing the amount of time it
takes to do very hard and valuable work.
So, there's one backdrop here that to
keep in mind. Uh I'm in the hardware
space. Light matter is building photonic
interconnects that link up AI
supercomputers.
Um and one of the things we're tracking
is the amount of power that's being used
uh for building these systems. And you
can see in the white curve, this is the
Frontier AI uh model power consumption
curve versus the US energy grid growth
rate. You're something like you know um
a few percent per year growth in energy
coming online in the US. And AI is
really going to smash through uh what
the US energy grid is going to be able
to bring online. There's a lot of work
on uh nuclear reactors. They'll have 10
100 MW nuclear reactors per gigawatt
data center. I just want to think about
a gigawatt with you for a second. Um a
house is a few kilowatts. A rack is
starting to be a megawatt. A thousand
racks is a gigawatt. This room could
hold a few hundred racks. So, you think
about the energy density of what we're
talking about. It's pretty incredible.
So, how are we going to close this gap?
How are we going to let AI continue on
this progress curve?
Uh I've got an idea and I'll tell you
all about it.
So, it turns out that interconnect is
actually the principal challenge. How
you allow GPUs and XPUs to communicate
is the principal challenge today in uh
enabling this roadmap uh for driving
agentic AI workloads and enabling growth
in the amount of computation that we can
do.
And that comes from first principles,
but I'm going to jump to the conclusion
uh first here given a 10-minute talk.
With ultrafast interconnects, at
Lightmatter, we use light to connect
GPUs and chips. We have single uh single
wave guides that transmit 1.6 uh terabit
per second per optical fiber. That's
1,600 homes worth of bandwidth in a
single optical fiber. What we're able to
do is improve time to train by 3x.
So, the same number of GPUs running the
same workload, three times faster time
to train. So, your data center finishes
that training job for the next fabled
model in 1/3 the time, and you can
train, you know, maybe the next two
versions over that that month that you
were planning to do. Uh significant
improvements in pre-fill and decode.
These are phases of inference, 3x for uh
pre-fill, and 11x interactivity, tokens
per second per user, for decode.
Um so, linking uh computer chips
together, these XPUs, these GPUs using
light, is going to deliver an enormous
per- performance uplift for AI
workloads.
And why is this happening? What's the
What's the fundamental thing that we're
driving towards? Uh what is the photonic
technology that we build at Lightmatter
enable? It enables you to build gigantic
computer systems that behave as a single
brain. These are strong scaling systems
in computer science, if you want to talk
about it that way. Strong scaling
systems. So, normally, uh you've got two
computer chips, and you'd like them to
run a workload together, and you'd like
to get two units of performance. And if
I have a thousand, I'd like a thousand
units of performance. The challenge is
that most workloads are not
embarrassingly parallel. You can't run
them in parallel like that. They need
synchronization. They need to share
parts of the operation. And so, how do
you build a computer that acts over a
thousand chips like a single chip? Well,
at the limit, you want to have zero
latency in communicating between GPUs,
and you want to have infinite bandwidth.
If you had zero latency and infinite
bandwidth, well, there's really no
difference between these uh GPUs that
are many meters away. So, so that's what
we do at Lightmatter. We build
interconnects that are so blazingly
fast. We already have chips that are 114
terabit per second. State of the art is
about 10 terabit per second. Uh we have
fibers that are 1.6 terabit per second.
State of the art is 0.2. There's 10x's
all over the place. What we're doing is
we are approximating this perfect
interconnect and this perfectly strong
scaling supercomputer. Over the next 2
years, you're going to see the first
systems with a thousand GPUs or XPUs
communicating and acting as a single
giant GPU or XPU. And this is going to
drive those inference and training
results that I talked about earlier.
So, this is what the tech looks like.
This is one of our chips, M1000. It's
the fastest optical communication device
in the world, 114 terabit per second.
You can see the optical fibers on the
top and bottom. Each one of those fibers
is moving 1.6 terabit per second of
data. Uh 1.6 ter- 1600 houses. This chip
moves 114,000
houses worth of bandwidth.
That's That's how fast it is. The cables
that connect North America to Europe are
about 200 terabits. That's less than two
of these chips. This is what's coming
and this is what's going to enable these
very large AI supercomputers that act
like a single chip.
And I'll leave you with this. This is
kind of what the systems look like. On
the left, we're showing one of our M1000
racks. This single rack is several
petabit per second of IO. So, the entire
world's traffic, internet traffic, is a
single rack from Lightmatter
M1000 there on the left. And we build
out data centers today because one of
the big challenges in computer science
and scaling these
AI workloads and AI platforms is
reliability. You have, let's say, a
hundred thousand GPUs in a data center
and 10 million connections that are
linking them together. Those 10 million
connections, they better not have any
errors. If there are errors, they're
going to freeze the AI training workload
run, they're going to crash your
inference workload. We have to make sure
that these these systems are extremely
reliable. And at Lightmatter, we build
out entire validation data centers where
we're operating hundreds to thousands of
these platforms and proving that they
just won't crash. They're going to be
rock-solid as they transport the kind of
data on the scale of, you know, the
internet between the continents.
And so, with that, I'll thank you guys
for for the time and I hope you enjoy
the day today.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you so much for that talk, Nick.
Now we have Grace A. Steiner, IBM
Fellow, IBM Research, to talk beyond the
harnesses, platform solutions, and agent
reliability, security, and efficiency.
>> Thank you very much. It's great to be
here.
Um
I believe we're entering the new the
next wave of platform application
platform evolution.
Uh the first wave being when we
separated hardware from software and
developed the first um
high-level programming languages.
The second being cloud computing when we
started creating distributed
applications across the data center and
the globe.
Uh both of these uh waves resulted in
creating a new operating system. And by
operating system, I mean a foundation
that separates application from uh
hardware from from infrastructure
through a layer of abstraction, but also
foundation that offers certain
primitives that applications can rely on
to achieve resiliency, scalability,
and efficiency.
AI applications are without any doubt
the most non- the most non-deterministic
and unreliable component that has ever
been introduced in enterprise
architectures. And I believe they will
require a new foundation, a new
operating system, as well.
Now, AI applications are applications
that they can run on existing
foundation. The problem really is that
this foundation doesn't really do much
to help solve the novel challenges that
are
occurring with these applications. And I
personally like characterizing these
challenges in two groups. They're
structural and semantic.
Uh structural challenges are because
these applications have open-ended
instruction set.
By instruction set, I mean the set of
operations that an agent can execute on
an external world. They decide which of
these instructions to use at run time,
and they order them at run time. Now,
that breaks a few very important
assumptions that existing platforms
make. Zero-trust security becomes very
difficult because zero-trust security
depends on understanding interaction
patterns between applications a priori
at configuration time.
Uh recovery becomes very difficult
because traditional techniques like
compensations and rollback become
intractable to implement. And of course,
these applications are not fully
testable in pre-deployment.
Um another problem is the lack of
separation of instructions and data in
the context, which is what agents are
working off. That's why we are seeing so
many novel security threats associated
with agents. And agents communicate
exchanging in context, so we are losing
execution separation between different
agents. And that essentially means that
controlling blast radius of resiliency
and security issues becomes very
difficult. And now there comes this
entire semantic side that Ion Stoica has
been talking about. Um that we are not
able to fully specify agent goals. It's
very difficult to express what agents
should do in the in the in the
narrative, but it's even harder to
specify what agent shouldn't do. And we
still lack any formal methods of
expressing
agent's goals and validating agent's
goals.
It doesn't help that
AI models, the agents, are not good in
reporting on their own status. We
essentially do not have any reliable
error codes. All this means that
understanding if agent is working
correctly, if it's succeeding, detecting
its failure, and understanding its
liveliness, so if it's making progress,
if it's converging towards the goal or
not hanging, all of these problems
become very difficult. And if we cannot
determine
what the problem is, we cannot recover
from from this either. And of course,
there is also a semantic gap between how
agent is thinking and
and designing what it should be doing,
and the and the
schema-based nature of a real-world
interfaces that with constantly changing
interfaces leads to leads to
mismatch and new errors being
introduced.
So,
how do we address these problems today?
Well, all of this is done in a bespoke
manner in the application layer. So, we
develop frameworks, we develop
harnesses, and we have plenty of them.
Every few months we see a new powerful
type of agent or harness being developed
that tries to tries to address these
problems and
and
and prove
provide proof of existence that the that
the solution exists.
Um but that creates a lot of
fragmentation. These harnesses are
actually very hard to develop. You need
to have a lot of expertise. Now, we are
clearly in the experimentation phase.
And when you look at the history, we see
that in the previous waves of innovation
the same thing happened. At the
beginning we have multiple versions of
of Unix. When container and cloud native
era started, we had lots of versions of
containers, lots of container
orchestration platforms, and entire
divergent ecosystems around that. But
eventually, the industry has identified
common patterns, standardized on them,
and consolidated. So, we ended up with
Unix and POSIX semantics for in the
first wave, and the Kubernetes and the
ecosystem around Kubernetes in the
second wave. We believe something like
this will need to happen in the AI era
as well.
So, that's what we and my research group
are exploring.
And the way we approach it is by looking
at the types of agents that we are
running in our organization. And we
essentially have three types of agents.
We have those that we have implemented
ourselves using our some framework or a
some SDK, so we have complete control
over them.
We have agents that are, you know,
well-known harnesses that we can control
via hooks and plugins.
And we have black-box agents that we
cannot do anything about. Those we can
only
control by observing them on the
outside.
So, what we are building is a layer of
interception that can interact integrate
with all of these styles of agents in a
and provides a uniform way to observe
and modify all interactions that these
agents are making with the external
world.
Using that layer of abstraction, we are
adding control functions to manage how
agents are behaving. Our first approach
first problem that we've tackled has
been security, and particularly the
zero-trust security,
implementing multi-tier, multi-layer
permission system to control how agents
are what agents are allowed to do. This
included uh implementing um identity use
and using that identity to implement
delegation flows with authorization,
then policy-based access, and then
finally, intent-based access to evaluate
if what agent is doing is actually
aligned with user's objectives.
We have moved since to also start
looking into the semantic layer of
agents. So, can we in this business
logic-independent way, outside of
agents, uh control the context and
manage manage context that agents are
using? Uh can we manage the correctness
of tool calls? And
do data flow analysis to to understand
how data is flowing and and control
that.
We are pursuing this in the project
called called Rosso Rosso CTL. Our web
pages contain more information and also
contain
deeper results of various benchmarks and
experiments. And my colleague Maya has a
poster that she's going to present
today, so I encourage you to stop by and
learn more about what we have done. Now,
crucially, we are not inventing we are
not replacing the existing platform. All
of
all of the things that we are doing are
built on existing cloud platform. We
leverage existing standards and extend
them.
Uh so, standards like OAuth 2, SPIFFE
for identity,
known policy languages. We are
orchestrating this on Kubernetes.
And our gateway-based approaches are
originally based on Envoy proxy, but now
we are moving to a more efficient
Rust-based proxy implementation based on
project Praxis.
Um we have encouraging results.
Uh we can demonstrate cost reduction
even with state-of-the-art agents from
context compaction. We can demonstrate
consistent improvements to
tool calling accuracy, which translate
into improvement to agent quality. And
we can certainly demonstrate that we can
transparently do permissioning for these
agents.
Um another important part of the
evolution of the
platform or evolution of applications is
of course application patterns. And we
believe that for agents, the right
application pattern is serverless.
Serverless pattern separates agent loop
as a stateless component uh from
durable session lock where the context
is being managed and
execution tier uh provided by diverse
set of sandboxes.
I would believe that leads to better
resiliency, better accuracy, better
better better performance, and better
scalability.
And again, um we have um encouraging
results. We can save a lot on
infrastructure cost, particularly for
agents that are
uh that are model bound. We can flexibly
allocate sandboxes, so not all agents
not all agents require most expensive
sandboxes, and they can be quite
expensive. And we can also reuse
sandboxes for certain type uh certain
types of agents where
security policy allows that. So, to
summarize that, um we do believe there
is a new wave of platform that is going
to be built. We've started on that
journey. Uh we are very interested to I
am very interested in talking to you
about this if you agree or disagree. And
certainly if you work on any project in
this direction,
um I would like to know about it, and we
would like to partner with you. Thank
you.
>> [applause]
>> All righty, and now we have Tim Hockin
with a distinguished engineer for Google
speaking is Kubernetes good for agents,
infrastructure solutions for
agent-shaped problems.
>> Hello. Oh, there I am.
Thank you all for coming out today. I
didn't realize this conference was on a
weekend when I signed up for it. So, I
really appreciate you all coming out
instead of getting a day off work. My
name is Tim. You may be familiar with
some of my previous projects,
Kubernetes. If so, I apologize in
advance.
Given my background, I tend to look at
this Agentyc AI problem as an
infrastructure problem. I see it from
the bottom up.
The customers that I talk with come to
me and they say, "We've got these
agents."
Like your explanations of the breadth of
agents was exactly on point. There's a
million kinds of agents, but they all
come to us with similar problems
saying, "We need to run them. We need to
run a lot of them. We need the
efficiencies that we're not getting."
Um
Agents, Agentyc workloads are very
different from traditional applications,
which is really it's caused people to
ask whether Kubernetes is the right
platform to run these things. It warms
my heart to see Kubernetes mentioned on
other people's slides,
but I think it's a fair question.
And so, given this audience, I'm not
going to go too deeply into how agents
are different. Touch on it just a little
bit. I apologize for racing through this
material. I'm happy to do it again in
the halls or talk whenever, you know,
after we're here for the next 2 days. Um
So, let's let's look at a couple of
things that make agents interesting.
Agents are very bursty. They tend to
work in in very short spurts and then go
idle for a long time, minutes, hours,
even days, weeks at a time. This means a
lot of idle resources if you approach it
naively.
Um agent workloads generally untrusted.
I think it's a pretty well understood at
this point.
Because of that, they have to run in
sandboxes, and we're always looking at
new kinds of sandboxing. Um, and they
have to run single-tenant cuz you can't
share a sandbox. That would kind of
defeat the purpose. Um, that means we
miss out on a ton of opportunities for
optimizations, specifically the
amortization of overheads.
Um, and lastly, they tend to have humans
in the loop, which makes them very
sensitive to the perceived latency of
these systems.
Taken together, uh, this kind of makes
it problematic to run them on
Kubernetes. Kubernetes was built for
things that run for a long time and tend
to be, uh, scale out, horizontally
scalable, and you can amortize your
costs. Um, so before jumping to a
solution, I'm going to touch on the
state of the art, what we've observed,
um, at Google and in the Kubernetes
world, of how people tend to run agents
on Kubernetes. And there's really only
two patterns with a few variations. Um,
so first is the obvious way. So
Kubernetes has this idea of a runtime
class, which lets you define a kind of
sandbox. So the default runtime class is
a Docker-style container, an OCI
container. Um, but we also have runtime
classes for gVisor and for microVMs, and
it is an extension point for Kubernetes.
So people can, you know, do interesting
research around that.
Some event causes the need for a new
instance of an agent. So, for example, a
user starts a chat session.
Uh, this obviously requires
instantiating their agent, a special
dedicated single-tenant instance just
for them, and each of those runs inside
of an agent, uh, a sandbox pod. Now,
there's some cost. Starting up a pod on
Kubernetes is not the thing that
Kubernetes does the fastest. It's not
optimized for that. It's not built for
that. It's fast, seconds usually, but
that's not fast enough. Um, and so
depending on what that agent does at
startup, it could take a long time, and
we've seen agents that load runtime
environments that can take 10s or 15
seconds or more. Browsers, like all
sorts of things.
Eventually, that pod becomes ready and
the user can chat with it and they send
their message to the pod and it comes
back and one turn is done, right? And
now what?
So, because pod startup isn't free, what
people tend to do is they wait for
another event. And how long should they
wait? Well, that really depends on what
your agent is doing and what the startup
cost was and you have to do some math
and it's different for everybody. Um
we've seen this range from tens of
seconds at the low end to tens of
minutes at the high end. And during
those tens of minutes, your your agent
is sitting there consuming resources
that can't be used by anybody else.
Eventually, and this of course this
might happen multiple times, right? At 9
minutes and 59 seconds the next turn
might happen and you start the whole
process over again.
Um
so eventually you get a timeout and
you're deemed idle and either you're
discarded entirely or we save your state
somehow and then we terminate the pod,
right? This is the standard Kubernetes
life cycle. Now, keep in mind this is
happening for every instance of every
agent for every user that is happening
on your system.
There are tricks we can play with warm
pools and there's
uh tricks we can play with suspend and
resume, um
but Kubernetes doesn't support those
things natively and so you're kind of
working around the system and it's
difficult to justify at this scale.
The second approach is uh for people to
build a DIY system on top of Kubernetes.
Um basically this looks like a giant
workload per machine inside that
workload is a manager application. Uh a
bespoke control plane is responsible for
scheduling things into those that that
mega sandbox. Uh the manager manages the
life cycle. Everything's opaque.
Kubernetes doesn't know what it's doing.
You end up reinventing large parts of
Kubernetes. It's fairly complicated to
build. It can be very efficient. Um it's
difficult to operate for smaller
companies, especially startups. Now, I'm
a huge fan of open and
Maybe you can tell because I work in
Kubernetes for the last 12 years. Um
I have a deeply held belief that when it
comes to infrastructure, open always
wins.
And so earlier this year we set out to
build something new that takes the best
parts of both of these models, leverages
Kubernetes where it can cuz almost
everybody has some Kubernetes in their
fleet, um and builds new components
where we have to. Um now I'm not going
to pretend that we've discovered
anything new. We have not done any
earth-shaking research here. What we've
done is take some of the best ideas from
all of our customers and our users and
try to glue them together into a way
that everybody can use. In the same way
that you put Kubernetes up on the slides
as the the middle box, I'm would like to
fill in the uh the the right-hand second
box for you.
So, Agent Substrate, and thank you for
mentioning it, um
is a project that we began earlier this
year um and have open sourced it. You
can go to this URL, it'll take you to
our GitHub. Um it's uh from a very high
level, the model is pretty
straightforward. We don't want idle
resources. We want to use suspend and
resume and cloud storage to uh multiplex
agents onto pre-warmed runners um and
aggressively suspend and resume agents
to take those 5 10 seconds to 10 minutes
of idle and drive it down to a single
second or even less.
So, let's talk about the goals. Um
we're Google, so we tend to see things
from the large-scale point of view. Um
we're shooting for very large
deployments. We're looking at billions
of sessions under management. We're
looking at thousands of tens of
thousands of activations per second, and
we're looking at driving the wake-up
time down into the
low three-digit milliseconds.
Quickly, I'll introduce some terms. Um
we have an actor, which is sort of a
stand-in term for agent or sandbox or
thing that acts like an agent.
We have an actor template. Uh if an
actor is a cookie, the actor template is
the cookie cutter. Uh it includes
details like what kind of sandbox tech
is it? A gVisor or a microVM? Um
notably, there can be many different
templates inside of a single substrate.
We have a worker, which is usually a pod
running in a Kubernetes cluster. This is
the thing that actually consumes
resources. It waits for an assignment of
an actor, and then it runs that actor.
It can run many of them in serial, um,
and a cluster can have many workers.
Um, and then Eightlet is sort of our per
node manager for all of the workers on
that node. We need this for reasons
around networking.
Um, and then lastly, Eightnet is our
enlightened proxy, which will trigger
wake-ups on receipt of traffic. Let's
see how those fit together.
Start with a Kubernetes cluster. Any
modern cluster should work. We support
running in kind, so you can run it on
your laptop. Uh, the cluster admin
deploys an instance of agent substrate,
which includes an API server and storage
layer,
a uh, controller, which synchronizes
data in and out of Kubernetes,
uh, one or more worker pools, which
create deployments, which create pods to
run your workloads in,
Eightlets to manage all those workers,
the Eightnet proxy, which knows how to
pass traffic from the outside world to
the inside world.
And then the substrate admin can create
one or more actor templates. And the
controller sees these and does some prep
work. Specifically, it spins the actor
template up, takes a snapshot of it, we
call it the golden snapshot, stores that
somewhere, so we can use it later.
Now, shifting view quickly to the
substrate layer, which sits on top of
all this, I'll warn you, some of this is
aspirational, we're still working on it.
Um, we have our API server, router, and
workers.
Um, someone, a higher-order system,
creates an actor from that template.
Uh, for example, uh, the same chat
agent.
Um, the chat app does whatever front-end
work it needs to do, authorize, or
whatever, and then it creates an actor.
Note, creating an actor doesn't run the
actor.
Um, in this hypothetical app, the user
talks first. So, the user sends a
prompt, which is received and routed to
the 8net proxy,
uh it wakes up the actor, assigns it to
a worker by sending a message through
the router,
uh and then talks to
the um
worker on a on a uh
private connection. Um since this is a
new actor, it wakes it up from the
golden snapshot. The 8net proxy forwards
the message on to the now running actor.
Um and the cool part is this happens in
a couple hundred milliseconds and we're
working on that optimization still.
Um as soon as that turn is done, the
actor is probably idle, so we can uh
tell it to go back to sleep and suspend
it. We call it pause. Uh if we pause,
take the snapshot and shuffle the data
off and now the worker is unassigned.
It's available for use by another actor.
All of that can happen as fast as your
um API operation or your agent
transaction happen. Um again, if another
agent if another prompt comes in, we'll
start the cycle again. Um
and eventually no more messages are
received and we will shuffle the data
off to cloud storage and it'll go to
sleep for the night. Um looking at the
whole thing from the highest level, a
Kubernetes cluster can be a one-node
cluster on your laptop or it could be
200,000 nodes in the cloud. Each of
those nodes can run multiple workers. Um
each of those agents are idle 99.999%
of the time, so you can do the math and
see we're driving up to those billions
of numbers. Um
Whew.
Agent Substrate is an open source
project. Uh it is still pre-production
grade, but we're working really hard to
get it out uh into a workable state by
the end of this uh
fall and come take a look at it if
you're interested in it. Take a look at
what we've done. Bring us your feedback.
The most useful thing that we can get
from people is experience and
requirements and context about what
you're doing with agents. We'd love to
hear from you. Thank you, everybody.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you for the fantastic set of
talks. We now are going to have a
workshop on why your agent needs a
wallet, agentic commerce on Arc with
USDC and nano payments with Harsh Il
Bengali leading the way.
Uh if you'll allow a little bit of time
to get the session set up, uh we will be
underway in just a minute or two.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah.
>> Good morning, everyone.
Uh nice to see so many of you here on a
Saturday. Um yeah, really excited to uh
showcase the work that Circle's doing uh
in the agent AI space. So, my name is
Harshal, and I'm a staff software
engineer at Circle.
So, often times um when I'm meeting AI
developers at meetups and conferences, I
get asked this question, um so you're
with Circle,
isn't Circle a stablecoin company?
Yes. Um and why is uh
what's Circle's role in the agent AI era
and agent AI space?
It's a fair question, but the answer is
fairly straightforward uh because Circle
issues USDC, and USDC is the world's
largest regulated digital dollar.
And turns out that
the thing that your agents get stuck at
is payments. And we have spent many
years making payments faster and
cheaper.
Uh and this is the gap that we're sort
of going to look at today
in this workshop.
So,
when we are often talk about making AI
agents powerful and autonomous, we are
thinking of
powerful models, more tools, um better
uh you know, better quality eval
and
those are the right things to look at,
but
one of the things that happens is
these days the models are strong enough
that they can plan your task for you,
they can write code for you, but the
moment they face a paywall uh or the
moment they are asked to like log in or
sign up on behalf of you,
they give the control back to you and
that's the that's the gap.
So, what we'll look
uh in this workshop and I'd want all of
you to participate uh is
how an agent is empowered the moment you
provide it with a wallet and
empower it with the ability to pay for
it
all the things that it needs on the go
and how to do it in a secure way.
So, let's get started.
Let's talk about like how
Um let's see.
Issues with this slide.
Um
let's start mirroring again.
Uh
Yep. Uh
there seems to be an issue with the
mirror.
I think the
Yeah, I'll get up.
Come on.
Give it a second.
All right, there we go. Awesome. Thank
you.
So, uh let's sort of like look at
where we were in uh a couple of years
ago, right? In 2023, mostly we were uh
interacting with LLMs uh via ChatGPT uh
and just like prompting.
Uh 2024, things got a bit more advanced.
We started like running some evals, um
the getting a better understanding of
how uh our agents work.
2025 was all about MCPs, uh skills,
orchestrating agents. So, having an
agent manage a fleet of other agents
uh and
doing more powerful work.
And in 2026, we believe that
um
that's the year of
where agents will go pay for things and
pay each other, and the agentic economy
is truly here and it's about to stay.
And the early numbers are quite
promising. So, if you look at the
numbers um
in the last 30 days alone,
agents paid for 24 million dollars worth
of information on the internet.
And 98.8%
of it was settled in USDC.
Now, when you think about
just traditional finance numbers, 24
million is not a lot. But, uh
it's projected by
2030 that the agentic economy will be 5
trillion dollars.
And
now the question is,
why do agents get stuck?
Um so, when let's sort of like
look back at how the internet was built.
So,
the internet for the last 30 years
catered for one type of customer, which
is humans. So, all the payment rails,
the
the monetization schemes, everything was
custom-made for this one type of
customer, which is humans. So, you you
had your sign-up flows, your
subscription models, your paywalls,
and ads, right?
But now,
there's this new type of customer, which
is the AI agent. And the AI agent does
not interact with the internet or
behave in the same way as a human does.
Their ability to consume information is
orders of magnitude higher than any
human.
And you can prove it, right? Like you
run a simple like deep research query
with your Claude, and you'll see that
like it's able to like read through like
hundreds of pages of information in a
few seconds.
Now, some of those pages some of those
articles on the internet
behind a paywall.
Rightly so, because you know, the
merchants are like, "Okay, this is
premium content. I want a human to pay
for it." So, once they hit a paywall,
they can't go ahead and access it, and
the quality of your research
just sort of like is that
degrades because it cannot reach that
premium resource.
So,
then on the other side, you have the
merchants. And
the merchants build these paywalls
because you they wanted to monetize
content.
But now they're realizing that there is
this new customer base, and instead of
like charging them a subscription fee, I
can just
charge a fraction of an amount for the
agent, so that they can just pay for
that specific piece of article or that
piece of
you know, data or some
inference, and make money off it.
So, why uh just like why not monetize
this? And agents are increasingly uh the
the traffic is actually going up
compared to like humans. So, there's
this opportunity for merchants to
monetize their uh premium content and
resources.
And they do that by just offering the
same services for a fraction of a
uh
of a price for
uh a traditional subscription.
And
that's the the the whole problem.
Uh but
then you you might ask, "Okay, um
why not just have my agent manage my
subscriptions or give it a credit card?"
Well, um
it works. You could give your agent like
a few uh subscriptions and API keys to
manage. Uh
but
does it scale? Because today you want uh
task X, tomorrow you want something
else, and
uh how can you um pay or subscribe for
something that the agent just discovered
as part of its research and is like,
"Oh, I want to access this resource. I
think it's valuable." Uh and now it
stalls. So, that's the challenge. And
then
you can say, "Sure, like let's just use
credit cards." Well, um
that's fine if you're okay giving your
agent your credit card information,
but the economics don't work either.
Because as I mentioned earlier, uh
merchants are exposing these um end
points or these resources to agents at a
fraction of a cost. So, if an agent,
which is making these high-frequency API
calls for premium content, has to pay 1
cent, and he has to uh the agent has to
like then pay 3% or 2.5% of credit card
fees, the economics just do not work.
Right? So, so that's why uh traditional
payment rails aren't the best way of uh
way for AI agents to like pay uh as they
go.
What agents need is payments that work
like the internet.
Payments that are real-time,
low cost, programmable, and always on.
And that's why
Circle built the Circle agent stack. So,
it's a full-stack platform for the agent
tech economy.
And
let's look at it
by visiting agents.circle.com.
And from here, like if folks
have their laptops on, we can start sort
of the workshop where
we'll have like a few colleagues of mine
over here who are probably collecting
emails, and we'll be distributing some
USDC for you to like try this as we go
on an interactive journey where we try
to like build a
a business. So, let's see
how our agents can,
you know,
build something for us when they're
empowered with a wallet.
So, let's look at
agents.circle.com.
So, what's
agents.circle.com? So,
you have a single place where your agent
can hit a pay day API. All you need to
do now is just copy this prompt in one
click, and
use your Claude, Cursor, or favorite
like agent coding tool,
and then
let it run.
So,
it will install a CLI. It will generate
a wallet. The setup instructions are
very simple.
My colleagues can help you out if you
run into any issues.
But, let's also look at the marketplace
because I talked about,
you know, agents being able to like pay
for things as they go, but what do they
pay for? What are the services? And then
there's the question of discoverability.
Like how do they discover
what services are out there? And that's
where our agent marketplace comes into
the picture. And the discoverability
layer. So the CLI, once you download and
set it up, you're able to it's able to
like discover these paid services. And
you have around
a thousand endpoints from various
providers
spanning a wide range of
categories,
which is you have
endpoints for image generation, for
example,
which just cost like 2 cents
per image.
You no longer need to have subscription
for a specific image generation model.
Then let's look at some financial
analysis tools.
You you have like access to, for
example, crypto prices. And prediction
market. Prediction markets are fun. You
can like have your agent, you know, uh
give give it some funds and like make
bets on the prediction market.
And
that's one thing. Social intelligence.
So if you if you want to like plan some
GTM motions or want to like do some
sales motions, so how do you do that?
Like
just pay as you go
for the content that you need. And it's
one of the favorite things I use is the
Reddit endpoint. So I just I'm just able
to like
query some Reddit information for just
like 2 cents.
And
and then there's your web search. So
uh better quality web search for your
agents for a fraction of a cost.
So with that, um
if folks are ready, I'm going to give
I'm going to pause for a couple of
minutes here. So if folks are want to
like start the workshop with me and
install the the
and then we can take it from there.
So, um
if folks need
to install the CLI, all you got to do is
just go to agents.circle.com
and click on find your agent in one
prompt. It copies a prompt, and now I'm
here in cursor. I already have the CLI
installed, but uh you can just run this
command, which will set up the skill and
the CLI for you.
And then it will prompt you for an OTP,
and you can log in.
And um just
to walk you through my setup over here,
uh you don't have to do do same thing. I
have two terminals running here because
on my left-hand side, I have a what I
call a vanilla agent. So, it's an agent
that does not have access to a wallet.
And on the right-hand side, I have my
agent which has the Circle CLI installed
and can pay for things as we go. Uh and
the task that uh I'm trying to do today
uh
with you all is uh I've always dreamt of
I love coffee. So, I've always dreamt of
like, you know, uh owning my own uh
coffee grocery. So, what we're going to
do today is see uh what we need to set
one up, what's the business plan, and
can we do some
um you know, uh
some tasks associated with that. It's
going to be a fun
uh
small uh activity and you you guys can
do the same thing or like, pick
something that you'll like as well. So,
yeah, I'll give it 30 more seconds and
then we can get started.
>> All right. Um
Cool. So, let's get started. Um so,
yeah, the first prompt is fairly basic,
which is okay, I want to start a coffee
roastery in San Francisco. So, can you
come up with five names and look, uh you
know, if if I want to build a website,
uh I want to know if the domains are
available. So,
uh let's see what uh uh
agent without a wallet on the left-hand
side does and the agent with a wallet on
the right-hand side. So, you'll start
seeing that um
the results as we uh start doing
slightly more complicated things, the
results uh will show a difference in
quality. So, let's let's look at this.
So, uh the left left-hand side one is uh
just running through Whois to see um
uh if the particular domain is
available.
And
on the right-hand side, uh you can see
that
you know, the agent is first checking
whether there are funds, what's the
budget, and it's making uh API calls to
the CircleCI via the CircleCI
listing the wallets,
and checking the balance, and then is uh
looking through the marketplace to see
what uh endpoint do I have uh to
essentially
uh
look for domains. So, you have one,
which is stable domains, and it's the
description uh it was able to like
browse through the marketplace to see
what matches my requirement, and now
it's uh because it matched this
description, it's actually inspecting
that and now it's going to give us
the result. So,
So, you can see like some domain is
already taken. So, it's all
The left agent already finished. So,
Yeah, obviously it's flagging that there
could be some IP issues with Carl and
everything. So,
we'll wait for this agent to finish.
You see like this agent actually made an
API call for 10 cents.
Sorry, 1 cent to
check
if the domain actually is taken or not
and how much it's going to cost to
actually purchase an available domain.
So, this information
I think you can find the same
information
with a free web search, but it's not as
accurate obviously and this one is
definitely true like, okay, because it
was able to like query a registry and
figure out, okay, it needs 20 bucks a
year for me to like purchase a specific
domain.
So,
um
let's
um okay, it's
picking Sutro Roasters. So, I'm just
going to
uh give it and say
let's go with
I like
Bay Area's Coffee.
Um I'm hoping there's
and I'm just going to copy it here and
let the two agents run.
So,
once that's finalized, the second task I
want to do is
Okay, now I essentially want to know the
competition. I want to know uh
it's essentially a task about market
research. So, what do I need to do to
stand out amongst my competitors?
Uh and I want some quality like uh
access uh to some uh journals and how to
like roast the best beans and which
beans to import and
some information like that. So, let's
That's my next task. So,
let's
start with that.
And I shall
So, yeah, it asked a follow-up question,
which is like, okay, check for
trademarks, etc. So, I'll just save this
for now and
and let's start.
Um yeah, also the other thing I did was
um I've updated the Claude.md file from
uh in my agent over here to always give
a very specific summary for the uh
uh as part of each step here so that
everyone understands like what happened
and how much was spent uh as part of
that particular step. So, if you see
like it spent like 12 cents
uh total. So,
let's begin the next task.
Any questions thus far like while the
agents run, I'm happy to like take any
questions.
Okay.
All right.
So, uh again, on the left-hand side, the
agent is just doing your regular web
search and it's finding everything
that's uh available on the internet for
free.
On the right-hand side, it's the agent
specifically calling a Google Scholar
API for and
then figuring out
how to actually
fetch those
paywalled articles, find quality
research, and yeah, take it from there.
Yes.
Oh, sorry.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's a great question. So, we
right now curate our marketplace
with So, we have actually like looking
at the endpoints and testing it out
to ensure that, you know, the
marketplace it's not just like anyone
registering their endpoints.
And
the other thing you bring up great point
about security.
And I'm going to talk about like
security of your funds, right?
I was talking about how you could
potentially give your credit card to an
agent, right?
That's dangerous.
With Circle CLI and Circle wallets, what
you can do is you're not essential
you're not giving your wallet or your
fund to your agent. You're essentially
creating a wallet for it for it for the
agent itself. And it's their funds. So,
you're you're managing funds for
you know,
the agent itself. And you can have a
fleet of different agents and you can
assign specific budgets to each of them.
And even now in the CLI itself, you can
enforce
the max spends and limits on
hey, how many how much can I spend per
session? How much can I spend per
specific website? Or how much can I
spend it in a day? So, these are
thresholds and these are policies which
are enforced cryptographically
and you can then
be assured that your agent will act
within those guardrails and your funds
are safe. So, uh then you should be able
to like freely
fund your agent.
I hope like that answers the question
from the fund side.
Sorry. Uh
Yeah.
>> Um you said like a formal logic or a
formal verification mechanism at the
back end to um
I guess for the guardrails and the
verification aspect for such agents.
>> Um are you talking with regards to like
just spending?
>> Yeah, just managing the whole thing
basically. I mean, for example, you're
running this prompt and the whole
process of it.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh what plan it generates, how it's
verified, like how it's spending. I
mean, yes, of course, spending is the
final input.
>> Yeah. So, I think like this is obviously
a question that
we we are actively working on
and also some of the things that
I can talk about
with regards to like malicious spending,
again, is
we have like
blacklists and
you know, you cannot like transact with
like sanctioned addresses and stuff like
that.
I with regards to like what the model
essentially does. Um it's again like
that depends on the model harness and we
need to like do continuous evaluations
and we are doing on our end like
evaluations on how our skills and how we
can better improve those skills that we
install uh we provide uh to make like
better judgments.
So, yeah.
Question?
>> Yes. Yeah. Um
so, my son is in high school and I also
give him a wallet similar to this.
>> Yeah.
>> spend my credit card correctly.
>> Uh but what I learned is
you also need to teach him like the
concept of money and then
making money is hard so he need to spend
smartly.
>> Yeah.
>> So, do you do any research for your
agent? I know you have a
skills and careers but that's kind of
like just setting the rules.
>> Yeah.
>> But what to spend the money, how to
invest in like the
like there's multiple websites, which
one has a higher value for return?
>> Yeah, so right now I think we've not
enforced like such
sort of like guardrails or like rules
into the CLI that look for the cheapest
one or something. It's obviously like
based on uh your use case. Um and
it can
the CLI is flexible enough where like
you can sort of like add additional
skills within your project and set up to
sort of say that hey, if you're if you
need to like um
uh spend more than like $5 like now
we're nearing my budget limit so like
start looking for like cheaper end
points, right? Like similar to like how
you would like if your monthly AI usage
is like
coming to the limit, you you resolve to
like using cheaper models. So, something
like that. So, you can always like do
that but right now we do not have like
specific rules around like hey, which
one to select. The
you will actually like
as as I was doing a trial run yesterday
for this and I was observing how the
model was thinking, it did
the next in the next next task it I
asked it to like generate a logo and it
was able to like just make an
intelligent decision saying
you know
you're designing a logo for a company so
it has to be of great quality. So I'd
rather spend on the more expensive
agent which is good sort of like image
generation model than a cheaper one
because the the price difference is just
a few cents. So I think it's make the
agent is making that
sort of like decision intelligently and
you can always like tune it the way to
your liking. But I do really like the
analogy that you gave of
you know having a wallet for your son
because that is exactly like
how I think of this as a mental model
like you have
you know a
sort of like your
almost like agents that you're managing
and you're just like funding them
independently
and
and and in a secure manner so yeah.
So
thank you for the great questions, yeah.
>> Yeah, real quick I don't want to take up
a ton of your time but have you
considered opening up the ability to
register idle GPUs and agents to pay for
their own compute?
>> Yes, so there are endpoints actually
which allow you to like pay for
inference so within the marketplace. So
you can you should explore that and
if you are if there are enterprises
if anyone's over here that that wants to
like expose their endpoints, we we have
folks
at the booth here for the next two days.
Please come talk to us.
Yeah,
the marketplace will thrive when
enterprises and builders
understand that like you know there you
can monetize your you know
content and resources for the agent
Akira so yeah.
But great question.
Looks like
yeah, I'm going to
just skip past the research and looks
like it both the agents finished. And
let's just do a quick read through like
okay, yeah, it looked at some
scholarly articles and
it spent about
Yeah.
117 cents
um
to to generate this. I'm actually going
to
just tell the agent to
use the agent
So, I had a couple of wallets and one
ran out of it. So, it's thinking that
it's like nearing its limits. So, it's
spending to answer your question.
It basically like cut down some of the
research because it was
you know
nearing the budget. So, because there's
only like 7 cents remaining in my
wallet. So,
I just prompted it to like
essentially
use the wallet with more funding.
Now, let's look at um
yeah, the task that I was
suggesting uh
in the earlier conversation and that
uh oh, I couldn't copy this.
Let's design a logo for our roastery.
So, over here what you'll see is the
agent is going to now leverage a
model
which is specialized in generating
images.
Um and my
currently my cursor setup does not have
any image generation models. So, what
you'll see on the left-hand side is the
agent uh will try to essentially come up
with a logo using
uh whatever skills it has. Whereas, the
right-hand side model will just pay a
few cents and call the appropriate
specialist model and get uh a logo
generated. So, let's see how that goes.
Quick time check. Okay.
So,
this is what the uh
agent does. Uh
Again,
it does an estimate. Uh there's an
estimate call which tries to estimate,
"Hey, uh
for my uh like logo, like what's the
price?" And it comes back like saying,
"You need 6 cents for this." And
yeah, and now let's
wait for the image generation to happen.
Okay. Look at Let's look at
uh
this agent on the left-hand side.
It says, "Okay, it verified
uh
level
I'll just ask it to
Looks good.
Uh sh
build the logo.
And
so, now it just paid like
65 cents to GPT image 2.
and
because uh the image generation can take
some time, so you'll see that the agent
itself is actually just pulling uh
because
you call the
image generation API and then you wait
for the result, so it's uh it just
pulled for a few seconds uh
because it set a time out of
240 seconds and now uh now that the
agent
has returned, this is the logo that it
generated for
let's see, 65 cents.
How was that?
And oh, um yeah, not even I'm sorry, not
even 65 cents, it's 6 cents. My bad,
I've been like oh,
uh you know,
using
missed out on the cost there.
So,
on the left-hand side, the agent is
still
because it's not an image generation
model, I think it will uh still come up
with a logo, but it'll take a lot of
time and it'll just uh sort of build an
HTML
uh thing and we'll wait for it uh it.
And
since the agent on the left has already
completed its task, I'm just going to
go and
go ahead and tell it that
I want you to make a flyer for my
launch, so
do that. So, embed my logo, build a
flyer, and the next task that we'll do
and where you'll see that the
uh agent without a wallet will fail is
I'm going to ask it to just, you know,
email me all the details and then give
me a phone call and explain what the
research was done. The
regular models uh without a wallet just
do not have that capability. And let's
see if you're able to like accomplish
that in the next
10 minutes.
Um while the agents are
running, any more questions that
Yes.
>> Uh
non-related question at Circle
with this infrastructure, are you guys
also
looking into the commerce use case like
let's say buying shoes uh using the
agent?
>> Um we are actually Yeah, we're
trying to like
work with enterprises again to um
sort of
come up with
use cases, right? Like we we want to
like work with enterprises to educate
them that hey, there's a use case for
this. Uh now you're if you're a shoe
company, you could essentially like
um
expose or curate an endpoint such that
an agent I can do that from my own
cursor. I don't really have to like go
to the website and do something. Um so
yeah, we are encouraging and we're
actually trying to like work with
companies that and it's not just like uh
shoes, any
entity, any commodity that can be
purchased on the internet by a human
should be uh purchasable by an agent,
right? So that's that's sort of like the
end goal.
Yeah.
And yeah.
>> Uh so
how does the payment collection work in
in the agentic flow?
Uh for example, are you guys like fully
integrated with the ACH uh payment
methods.
>> Um
>> Uh
no. Uh so, we are using uh stable coins.
Uh are you familiar with stable coins?
So, yeah, the wallets these wallets are
crypto wallets. And uh once you fund the
wallet, uh you can on-ramp uh USDC has
many on-ramping uh
avenues. So, you can essentially like
on-ramp into your wallet, and then sort
of fund your agent's wallet. And then
the seller is the way um maybe
uh sorry, while the agent works.
Uh I'll explain like uh how this whole
agent uh interacts with the other uh
enterprises and other agents.
Um so,
for the last like 30-plus years, ever
since like the uh internet started like
with HTTP/2, the
uh
the own
the authors of the HTTP protocol, they
had envisioned that payments would
happen over HTTP. So, they they had this
status code 402 uh within the initial
spec, but it was kind of like dormant
until now because
uh there was just no means to like, you
know, do that. Uh so, but with the rise
of like blockchains and stable coins,
that has become theoretically possible
because what can happen now is
uh you
a seller can instead of like uh
preventing you from just accessing
something can return
uh a 402 payment header and says payment
required and provide the credential or
the details. And it essentially says,
"Send me
uh X amount of USDC on this particular
like blockchain address." Now, uh the
agent, uh because it has the CLI, is now
able to interpret that and realize,
"Okay, I need to pay 2 cents for this
image generation endpoint, right?" And
now,
it signs an authorization.
It's a EIP-3009 authorization. And
which essentially says
I authorize
to pay
specific address the said amount. And it
signs it with the key and attaches it
and re-requests that same endpoint. And
from there,
once the seller is actually receiving
that second request with that new
header
it it processes it it processes it it
figures out, okay, the payment is made
or at least has been authorized and I
can now release the said resource. Um so
now
because these transactions happen on
chain,
they
essentially get settled. So, there's no
ACH involved in in this. Does that
answer your question?
>> Yeah. So, would these transaction can
also be like integrated with the ADK or
MCP
from from the
>> Yes.
>> point of view?
>> Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Sorry, let's hope.
>> Uh yeah, this is back. Okay, and
Oh, all right. So
Oops, this is still not
>> visible.
>> Sorry, I'm having some
>> hello.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, hey. Yeah. So, I have a question.
So, I
does this agent have the capability of
memory for the cases like
you ask a specific questions that needs
a
very specific rules or law to follow and
then you asked exact same question or
very similar question and it can
retrieve and
be reliable enough to generate the same
or similar answer for the the type of
query.
>> Yeah, so again, that will depend on the
agent harness that you're using. So, if
you're using say cursor or cloud code,
it should just
and you're asking it from the same
session,
even if you're writing to the memory
like you're updating constantly your
agents.md, it should be able to like
look it up because Circle CLI is
essentially just think of it as just
another like connector on the by side,
right? Like
just like your you have an ability to
query Google Docs using a Google MCP,
Circle CLI essentially
like allows
an agent to pay for things. So, the
memory aspect and all of those are again
a function of the agent harness that
you're using. So, your cursor and cloud
code. Does that answer your question?
Um okay, so
>> I I have one more question.
>> Yeah.
>> Um you mentioned at the beginning the
idea that agents will need high
frequency
settlement for
for the transactions and also a low cost
that they can pay.
Um
I understand this is this is a POC, but
how far are we from having these kind of
capabilities in in the payment layer?
>> Oh, it's I'd argue it's no longer a POC
because as I mentioned in my earlier
slides,
we have like at least like around like
24 million plus
in volume by as of in the last 30 days
itself. So,
the whole X402 protocol as I was
explaining, the way agents enter pay for
these resources,
you can you can go online and like if
you see the volumes, they are
increasing. Like it started like I think
um late or early last year and now it
has picked up and
even though like it does not have the
same uh volume as traditional payment
rails, it
it's a start and it's a very promising
start
because now you're just able to like and
even on our side
I can speak for one of our customers
recently like you know they were able to
like make
request payments for 0.00005
cents. So it's like one micro like five
micro cents per API call.
>> But the the the the fee for settling
that that transaction is
>> zero because I can I can walk because
you raise a good point
that an actual blockchain itself like
even on the most economical blockchains
the settlement fee or the gas fees can
be a bit high
like compared to this like number that I
just stated which is like five micro
cent. So that's why we as part of the
Circle agent stack we've also built
another solution called nano payments
which is
which is on top of which essentially
allows you to make these like low sub
cent transactions at high frequency in a
gas free manner. So what you end up
doing is you essentially um
and this is a bit more technical but uh
you deposit funds into the gateway smart
contract which is what
you we did here and then from there
you're just signing these authorizations
and instead of like settling that
authorization on chain directly, what
the seller does is it calls Circle's
endpoints
and from there what we do is we
immediately like look at the buyer's
balance because the funds were deposited
in Circle's smart contract and we're
able to like deduct and reserve that
balance and from there
we instantly like return in a few like
50-100
milliseconds a
success or a failure based on you know
the balance. And then we
gather hundreds and thousands of these
authorizations
and actually batch them and net them
together in a trusted execution
environment and then broadcast them on
chain as one single transaction. So,
that's how we scale and we actually like
prevent like logging the blockchain
network with with hundreds and thousands
of these like very very low
sub-transactions.
And I'll I'm happy to like go deeper
into this like
after the talk. Yeah. Yeah.
A great question though. So,
And yeah, so now that our agent like I
said, so the agent was able to like
make
a
fairly good
flyer. Now I'm just going to ask it to
email this and give me a call on my
phone and just like walk me through the
research that it did and let's see what
happens. So,
and let's see if the call goes through.
So,
let me just combine the final two
prompts
in the interest of time and
I hope like this essentially like
gives a
people
an idea that if you
uh
you know equip your agent with a wallet,
there's a lot more a lot of
possibilities that it unlocks. So, and
we'll see like the agent without a
wallet just say that it just cannot do
this. So,
Yeah.
Two things I can't do from here which is
send the email or place a call. So, I'll
hand you both as things
you can execute in one step. So,
I had added my email and phone number as
environment variable, so it's able to
like fetch that.
And
let's
have it run and
So, the left the agent on the left-hand
side is essentially just going to draft
something and then hand it over to me
and say, you know, go send this email.
But, the one on the right will
sort of like go the whole route. So,
So, you see like it says like stable
email sends at two two cents, stable
phone at 54 cents. So, let me check the
schemas and see what I can do.
Okay, it's running into size.
Okay, I'll stop it from
Okay, it's actually going to compress
the image, so let it Let's let it do Let
it do its thing and um
Any questions I can answer in the
meantime.
Yes.
>> Thanks. Um
I noticed you're running it on low and
fast. Have you played with like Someone
asked about its understanding of money
and budgets. Have you played with
different reasoning levels and see what
it does with budget and stuff like
>> Yeah. Yeah, that's a that's a great
question. And again, as you probably
noticed it it's like Opus 5 with low
thinking and fast in the interest of
time because
if you run it like with even like
your regular models, it it can take some
time. So, it's it's essentially
I tried to like do this the other day
with
I think was it Fable or Sonic? So, it it
it built something so spectacular, but
it it took a really long time. So,
and for the lower um
I The other thing I also noticed was for
some of the
um
the lower models um
they are able to like make all of these
calls just right, but sometimes it's
just like the decisions and you know,
the summary you can you can see the
difference in like what it decides to
call. So, that's the difference you'll
see,
but it it's just a CLI at the end of the
day and it can like, you know, say call
that okay uh find me what can I discover
and then it's a something that even the
cheapest of models understand, right?
So, um CLI being this age-old thing that
every model actually understands. So,
Okay, so looks like the email was
delivered. Um and let me actually pull
up my
oops, work email.
Not yet.
Well,
let's check in a couple of minutes.
But, let's also wait for
my a phone call.
Uh
And there you go. So, now let's I'm
going to put it on speaker and
Hello.
>> Hi, it's your Hi, it's your research
assistant calling about Bear Ice Coffee,
got 2 minutes for the launch plan?
>> Yeah, sure.
>> Great. So, bears.coffee.com is available
for $20 a year, and your logo and launch
flyer are already in the inbox. The
differentiator is development time, not
roast level. A
>> Okay, sorry. Can you
Can you actually just tell me Can you
just tell me which beans should I buy?
Should they be
And from which of which roasters? I just
need that information.
>> For sourcing, Royal Coffee in Oakland
has Crown Jewel microlots at 22-lb
boxes, 220 to 455, about 1160 a pound
green.
>> Um great. And did you actually send
Um
Yeah, thank you.
And I'll
just grab the rest of the information
from the email. So, thank you so much.
>> Sounds good. Do you want me to register
the domain or run a trademark check
before I go?
>> Uh no, I think that should be all. Thank
you so much.
>> All right, talk soon.
>> And that was
uh
Yeah, that's how like you can
essentially like equip your agent and
make it more autonomous. So, yeah, that
was the end of the demo, and
I do want to like still see like if the
email landed, but if not,
let me just show you an email from uh
dry run. I don't know if it is in my
spam, but um yeah.
It There's a dry run email that I had
earlier this morning. So, um yeah.
So,
with um
agents.circle.com,
the final pitches Yeah, if you are a
seller if you are an enterprise that
wants to actually build,
um you can as a developer even like wrap
and monetize your endpoints in just a
couple of lines of code and you know,
list it on the marketplace. And yeah,
this is just the start.
There's a lot more to come and if you
found this
useful and insightful, please come talk
to us. We're here
at the booth. We have a booth.
Yeah. And that was that. Thank you so
much.
>> [applause]
>> All right, and now is time for lunch and
we'll have speakers again at 1:30. Enjoy
the lunch time.